hey folks welcome to the Dark Horse
podcast livestream this is what our 8th
sorry this is our 8th livestream I am
sitting with dr. Heather huiying as has
become our tradition we have been
fending off technical difficulties of
many different kinds and I would say at
this point aside from the audio the
video and our connection to the internet
everything is going smoothly smooth
sailing smooth other than those rather
than those three issues I wouldn't call
them trivial but you know they're part
of it all right so we want to start with
logistics on how we're gonna be dealing
with the Super Show yes why don't you
take lead on I will try so we have been
receiving many excellent and some not so
excellent but mostly excellent super
shot questions but it has become a bit
onerous and we are not we're giving
short shrift to too many of them because
we have been trying to we've been
reading all of them so this time we are
going to try another strategy which is
those super checked questions that come
in in this first live stream where we
are just talking to each other we will
look at over the break between the two
live streams and prioritize them based
on both monetary amount and then try to
do a very very first pass at you know
what questions are particularly
interesting and we'll spend a half an
hour only on those questions from the
first that come in during this first
live stream and if we don't get to all
of them which we probably won't that's
that's unfortunate and then we'll spend
a half an hour on the super chat
questions that come in during the next
live stream which we will probably have
to take in as as they come in so we're
going to limit the second live stream
the Q&A to an hour and see how that goes
and this is a moving target we're gonna
see how this goes this time and maybe
modify it next time it's a learning
process and a live-fire exercise all
wrapped into one so in any case also do
let us know we don't see every comment
do let us know what's working what's not
working we discovered some sound
problems last time hopefully you will
find that they have been successfully
addressed this time but every piece of
information is useful to us and we're
working on it and we're working on it
alone because obviously nobody is coming
to anybody's house to troubleshoot stuff
so we we being the two of us on-screen
but mostly Bret and our wonderful now 16
year old son Zachary Weinstein who's
doing the production end of things
Zachary is on the production end and
Toby is on the wall fishing and he's
becoming an expert at wall fishing which
makes me very proud you keep on assuring
me you've doing no wall lobstering but I
keep hoping we have not been forced to
wall lobstering yeah alright so I do
have a not a correction but an addendum
last time I mentioned a paper that I
thought was well worth people's time
written by one of the founders of
Instagram and it's a Kevin Systrom and
we will put a link to the paper in the
description but the short version is he
argues that the are not term that people
have become familiar with about how
likely an individual case of the virus
is to propagate to the term is are not
right which reads is r02 sure that that
tract yes on the paper it looks like our
subzero are not he argues that there is
a more important term that we need which
is our sub t which i think is just said
our sub t although it's not clear in the
paper which basically tracks the change
in transmissibility based on the
responses that people have the
behavioral responses and so this measure
is important for example if we want to
compare municipalities or something and
see what's working and what isn't not
just simply assigning an R nought to the
virus but assigning an R sub T to the
intersection between a virus and a
population is very useful so anyway it's
a good paper well-written
I strongly recommend it and we will link
it in the description alright I think
that's all I have you have correct I
want it well not a correction exactly an
addendum I want to add
or clarify to our discussion about
essentials last time where we spent a
while talking about flooring much to the
chagrin of some people and much to the
enthusiasm of others we were
specifically making an argument about
why flooring which has been included in
the list of prohibited purchases in the
Michigan stay at home order might be
considered an important psychological
tool for people in such times and in
times of lockdown giving them something
useful productive and creative to do we
didn't speak to the more obvious things
on the list things like seeds and
nursery supplies because a we've alluded
to those in the past and it just it's a
it's a really easy argument to make that
people should be allowed to buy seeds
with which to potentially grow their own
food especially as supply chains come to
be at risk so I'd like to reframe the
discussion slightly I know without
spending a lot more time on it but the
concept of essentials we were arguing
basically is a category problem but it
speaks to pre-existing category problems
nobody's being prohibited from buying
anything like anything that they might
eat actually you can buy flank steak and
blueberries you can buy mangos and whole
chickens and you could buy tofu and kale
to list six things that we've bought
during during lockdown right so long as
you can find them in the stores you can
buy those you can also though at the
moment if you can find them in the
stores buy Cheetos and Pepsi pop-tarts
and Twizzlers and redbull and doughnuts
not only are none of those things in the
second list essential though they are
actually bad for human health which by
now everyone knows even those even those
of us who eat those things sometimes so
nobody's attempting to draw that line
between the things that we ingest that
are arguably good for you and the things
that we ingest that are quite obviously
not if you can ingest it you're allowed
to buy it
and the because the fact that humans
need to take in calories is is
understood in part because it is so easy
to quantify and it's easy to quantify in
part because everything alive does it
and what we were trying to do by getting
at
the issue of flooring is get at those
things that are essential to being human
that are much harder to quantify but
that are qualifiable necessaries right
so because every evolved life form needs
to take an energy somehow if you're
photoautotrophs like a plant you convert
sunlight into energy into sugars and
then if you're a head of troph like us
you either steal that energy directly
from the autotrophs when you eat plants
or you steal it from
second order autotrophs when you eat
other animals and we can we can look at
it we can count it and sometimes we
count the wrong thing isn't certainly we
have been counting many of the wrong
things but it allows for this
reductionist approach and no one is
trying to draw the line between that
which you can take in to eat which is
necessary and that which you can take in
and it's not necessary but staying alive
isn't the only goal here is it nor is
keeping on just a second noise keeping
the economy intact the only goal if we
emerge from this disaster having
mitigated it with fewer deaths and there
would have been had we not more or less
stayed in place while hopefully getting
outside with fewer deaths but we emerged
broken and empty this will be a
large-scale depression that will be more
than economic that will afflict a
massive part of humanity that will be
far harder to emerge from yes and I
would also point out we have kids who
are growing up facing this unprecedented
thing and I know one of the things that
gave me a lot of insight into where we
are was in the early part of the
lockdown our our oldest son Zach who is
manning the equipment here said in
passing he asked me something to the
effect of how often this has happened in
my lifetime and I looked at him and I I
said this has never happened in my
lifetime or really ever this is
unprecedented and it changed the way he
saw things but of course you know a
child who's seen a much shorter slice of
history doesn't know how to calibrate
this and the reason I raise it is I can
imagine a lot of frivolous things things
that really truly are frivolous that
might be actually
arguably necessary in some parent-child
relationship to keep a sense of normalcy
and so the point I made last livestream
was I defy you to draw that line well
it's not that there isn't a line but the
point is that line actually has a lot of
richness between individuals and special
cases and you know if there's some candy
that is you know a child's favorite and
some parent is trying to deliver that
normalcy and the fact that the candy was
suddenly off-limits would be jarring I
mean I can easily see an argument for it
even if on balance the candy is probably
a negative with respect to its effect on
the immunity for example yeah so really
we're pointing out the difficulty of
drawing lines for which there are no
easily quantifiable hard borders we're
not saying that lines don't need to be
drawn some of them do a hundred percent
this is in part and large part what
government is for and we are fans of
good government but but the lines that
some of the lines that have been being
drawn are patently bad the closing down
of beaches when people are maintaining
social distancing is bad policy it's bad
policy and in fact it emerges fairly
strongly I would say this week in
several different papers one of which
we're going to get to but there is
stronger and stronger evidence that the
circumstances that are dangerous are
endure close quarters circumstances and
so in some sense by telling people you
can't go to the beach or you can't go
for a hike we have been denying people
something that they might do in favor of
pushing them in the direction of yeah
all right you're not out at the you know
nightclub but you are in close quarters
probably indoors where this thing is
being transmitted so in some sense we
have to be very cautious we don't yet
know how this thing functions and
telling people you shouldn't do that
because it stands to reason that you
might get sick in a public park when in
fact the data ultimately reflect the
unlikeliness of that scenario
is it's a problem and it also serves to
create snitches out of people right
which we are also beginning to see that
people are being encouraged to tell on
their neighbors if they perceive that
they are going out too much and in fact
as I understood the the mostly good
faith orders that were coming down early
early on there were no attempts to keep
people in place it was you know shelter
in place but go out for exercise for
fresh air
and you know people with dogs had this
easy excuse which is which is itself
very interesting why is it now that we
understand that our dogs need to get out
and move but we are less likely to
understand that we do as well yeah so
the whole idea of having bureaucrats do
this from something other than a place
of caution is I think legitimately
frightening and it's resulting in
backlash which i think is itself
frightening it's apparently the backlash
against the idea of controlling the
virus through you know wearing a mask or
avoiding social contact or all these
things that backlash is obviously a
danger to human health and even an
individual who chooses to flaunt the
rules is putting everybody who might be
downstream of them epidemiologically at
risk and some of those peoples are going
to die so it's not a minor question but
nonetheless the incoherence of the
policy is raising people's hackles with
respect to governmental overreach and
all of these things and so anyway some
sort of caution is clearly necessary
indeed all right did you have a next
topic you wanted to move to well
ultimately we're going to be talking
about that that Santa Clara County
serology testing paper but it doesn't
have to happen first as you like
actually let's start there many people
will have seen this paper do you want to
introduce yeah so Zack maybe can you
pull up the I don't know how to
pronounce this name actually been to v8
at all 2020 what's up let's see if I can
do it I for the first
time today I have stuff in front of me
let's see I may have it here Zack except
I can't see my no no I don't I don't
have it here Zack if you can pull it up
it's the one on the first page been
defeated all 20/20 right below the break
I'll be great ok so this came out at
this point I think it came out the day
before we're supposed to do our
livestream so it must be three days ago
maybe but I don't I don't see are you
gonna be able to show it to us ok
because I will I will need to see it
ever going to talk about it the message
is basically this is directly from the
discussion quote the most important
implication of these findings is that
the number of infections is much greater
than the reported number of cases title
of the paper being covered 19 antibodies
seroprevalence in santa clara county
california so what these authors did was
solicited via facebook people to come to
be tested for antibodies which is to say
past infection not current infection it
will not find current infection and then
they had drive-through testing they were
looking they tried to control for three
demographic so they tried to get equal
representation to match the demographic
background data okay well we will find
the link and put it in there I think
yeah so this is the santa clara county
been defeated all 2020 paper that is
widely discussed right now so they they
were looking specifically at i think age
race and ethnicity and zip code as the
three parameters that they were trying
to to match to the background
demographics of santa clara county and
we're you know shut down accepting
applications for the serology testing
when they got too many from certain zip
codes or too many from maybe certain
races or ethnicities and and then deidre
did drive
testing they also let people come with
up to one child from a household so
there was some non independence among
their among their data and let me just
say that there so their conclusion is
that like like I said that they have
that the in Santa Clara County anyway
there's a far higher background rate of
infection in fact I think the numbers
they have since I can't see the paper
now I can't actually pull up the
specifics fifty to eighty five times the
actual numbers that are being reported
from the more standard testing in Santa
Clara County which means if true if
those results are true then the case
fatality rate which is defined from the
dictionary of Epidemiology as the
proportion of cases of a specified
condition that are fatal within a
specified time the CFR the case fatality
rate would be far lower than has been
reported and this is you know consistent
with things that we've been saying for
you know well over a month at this point
right that the CFR is likely to be lower
than it's being reported but that does
not change most of the things that we
are that we need to do in order to
control this but let's just focus for a
moment on the actual study you want to
start by talking about a little bit well
let me just say you're gonna raise some
concerns about how the study functioned
yeah it does mirror data we're seeing
from elsewhere it's actually a fairly
close match for the data from Scotland
and then there's another study I believe
from Denmark that says the same thing
which is that the rate of infection is
actually far higher than we know that
when you test a population instead of
testing people who come through the door
for one reason or another you test the
population at large to see how many
people show signs of past exposure you
get a very high number which doesn't
change the number of people who have
died of the condition and so what we
find is that the transmissibility is
higher than we think but the mortality
rate is lower and so it would not be
surprising if Santa Clara County
reflected this very same pattern on the
other hand it doesn't make the study
viable if the study has methodological
flaws whether or not it comes to a
conclusion that's mirrored elsewhere
you know it's flawed so the question
really is what are the flaws and how
vital are they in terms of the
conclusion that was reached catch it
valid is it just noisy or is it
misleading in some way okay good so
there there are there are several
approaches that I could take to sort of
critiquing to and some some of them
bordering on nitpicking but I think
there's of two classes of critique of
this paper that are large enough to
warrant discussion here one is biases in
the subjects so as I said the methods by
which volunteers for serology testing
were chosen was through ads on Facebook
and those selected arrived at testing
centers by car for drive through testing
this means that those who were included
in the study had both means and interest
let's take those one by one means first
you have likely to be over selected for
relatively wealthy people at the very
least you're not including any homeless
people if you can only get testing when
you could show up with a car at a
testing site so this this though so this
this is going to miss count in maybe
both Direction simultaneously which
looks like noise right so if you if you
don't get some people in lower
socioeconomic classes who haven't been
tested because they didn't in have
previous means to get tested and
specifically homeless people you will
have you will have missed a large number
of people who were positive and thus
this could be actually an undercount
right the I mean I can I can see an
argument for going the other way but it
seems most likely that this means bias
goes goes one way and actually suggests
that these results in this paper are
conservative if everything else is
correct with regard to interest though
it clearly goes in the other direction
that those people who respond to a
Facebook ad a are you know looking at
Facebook at home that is to say they
again this is a question of means they
have the means to have to have a
computer at home through which to look
at Facebook but it's see it stands to
reason that
those people who think they might have
been infected in the past will have more
interest in going to be tested than
those who have no reason to think that
they've been infected and you know other
than an excuse to get outside you know
why is it that they're gonna go and
potentially put themselves at risk for
for such a study so given that given
that interest was a key driver I can't
you know it's impossible to quantify how
large a driver but a driver of how it is
that the subjects got selected for this
that is that is going to suggest that
that's going to go the opposite
direction of the way I think the means
question would which is to say it's
going to have driven the number of
positives up compared to the background
population which suggests that the case
fatality rate that they're reporting is
actually too high and that bit should be
lower so those that's that's the first
large class of critique that I have
about the paper I'm gonna say anything
about that or I would add one thing to
it which is a different kind of critique
altogether and it may well be that this
is so well understood epidemiologically
that it's a non-issue but yeah there is
a question in my mind given and I have
studied the immuno biology I will be at
a long time in the past but there's a
question about whether or not the
antibodies necessarily reflect a history
of infection or do they reflect a
history of exposure and my guess would
be that the level of antibodies that is
being detected would reflect a cleared
infection that is to say the immune
system goes into a pattern where it
becomes good at recognizing the invader
that it's already seen and that that is
what is being detected in which case it
would reflect an infection but it is
conceivable to me that especially in
light of how much doesn't make sense
about this virus or not doesn't make
sense but let's say surprising less
about this virus one thing we have to
ask ourselves is what happens to
somebody who has a high level of
exposure but doesn't contract an
infection
mm-hmm so it just worth it's worth
asking the question and I would love it
if somebody knows the answer and it is
clear that these antibody tests are
necessarily reflecting an infected
person now their infection has cleared
up that would be useful well in fact it
raises the question of high level of
exposure without contracting an
infection what would the antibody test
read what then does asymptomatic mean
asymptomatic is a category that could
mean either of those two things actually
if if they are in fact distinct yeah so
anyway maybe somebody in our audience
can conclude us into what we need to see
yeah so the other the other concern the
other major concern that I had about the
the scientific validity of this paper
even though again and we'll talk about
this more later I tend to believe that
the results are more true than the other
results that we're seeing that show a
very very low background infection rate
in populations
the authors demonstrate they go through
you know a fair bit of statistical song
and dance about explaining how they
assess the actual rate of false
negatives and false positives in these
tests and there other people online have
assessed whether or not they think that
those those are well done but they don't
seem to deal with the problem that with
a low base rate of infection in the
population even the higher rate that
they report here it's like the higher
rate that they report is up to close to
5% you know it's still very low right so
with a relatively low base rate of
infection of the population false
positives potentially outnumber true
positives in test results so I'm at
considerable risk of losing a lot of the
audience I'd like to walk us through
just a couple of made-up numbers just to
just to make this point because I think
a lot of people have been saying this
but with some made up numbers that are
simple it it might it might stick for
people so let's imagine a population of
103 people again this is just to make
the numbers easy in which
so let me say first that the authors of
this paper claim a false positive rate
while a confidence interval and
specificity between 98.3 and 99.9
percent which is staggering so that
would be a false positive rate of 0.1 to
1.7 percent which is very very low
listen the tests we're seeing suggest
about 5% false positive right so just
for ease of doing some some fake math
here I'm gonna use this 5%
sort of population 103 people we're only
three people have been infected that's
based on this generous background
infection rate of 3% or a 2.9 percent if
the false positive rate is 5% for the
test that is the test tends to give a
false positive 1 out of 20 times from 5
percent of the time maybe the 3 here are
actually positive test positive the flip
flip is here that false negatives will
be pretty rare in such a situation so
it's a 3 in the population of 103 will
actually test positive the remaining 100
though all of whom are actually negative
5 out of those hundred will also test
positive because you've got a 5 percent
false positive rate so in that case with
those very particular numbers that I
chose for ease of communication
you'll get 8 positive results in which 3
are actually positive and 5 are not
positive which means the majority of
people who show up as positive are
actually not so that's that's obviously
difficult to wrap your mind around and
let me just one more one more
mathematical thing and then I'll drop
the numbers if you take the same
population and the background infection
rate is now 15 percent rather than what
I said before 3 percent now you have 15
people out of the population of Hydra 3
who are actually positive only 4 people
out of the 88 remaining people who are
actually negative which means you got 19
positive results only 4 if I'm only 20%
or so are false positives so as the
background rate of infection in the
population goes up the risk that you're
positive is a false positive goes down
so I would also point out that there are
two potential kinds of false positives
here and which kind we are dealing with
has a lot to say about how
we can correct for this one is a false
positive where the test comes up
positive for no good reason and a second
test would suggest something was wrong
the second would be a false positive I
guess this would be the case if people
who had exposures but did not contract
the infection had sufficient antibodies
to trigger the test and we regarded them
as it as having cleared an infection
they would test positive each time they
had the test even though they have never
had the infection so it is possible and
I would argue that those are people we
want to include you know they've got
immunity oh well I don't know if they
have immunity in this iPod in this
hypothetical situation but let's put it
this way it's not that that situation
would be uninteresting it's that it's
signal for a category that we either are
or are not counting and so we need to be
very careful not to assume people into a
category they are not necessarily in and
a lot depends you know it may be that
experts on coronavirus infections know
very well what a particular titer of
antibodies implies and so they've ruled
it out for a good reason or it may be
that things are so novel here that we
may discover that there was a category
that we had lumped with another category
and changed the interpretation in a way
that was misleading yeah in fact what
I'm seeing is too much of the time and
this is just this is forced by the fact
that this is such a fast moving fast
emerging pandemic that categories are
being split into two that we are making
binary categories that really warrant
many more many more subdivisions and so
in general I think tighter you know
countable tighter of antibodies counts
as a yes and if you can't see it at all
it counts as a no and that's obviously
not a fine enough line to get at some of
the questions that that you and we are
raising but there's also you know
there's so much there's so much
important work to be done and this you
know will seem like nitpicking why quia
why aren't they splitting in and
thourough into more categories well then
you have this question just like we were
talking about with regard to what's
essential of where to draw the lines so
is there any are there any antibodies
present versus are there no antibodies
present is at least a line that everyone
can agree on that's Kwan
viable yes or no but but binary
situations that are actually in which
you can have zero and you can have some
to a lot that's actually a continuum and
it's it warrants a different kind of
statistical analysis that we just don't
have I think the time or the means for
yet and at the very least we can say
that the the phenomenology of these
infections is so varied and so confusing
that we know there are features of this
that are utterly continuous and leave
you scratching your head so whether the
infection itself in the test we're using
our truly testing binary circumstances
or whether their categories are missing
is an important question so if you've
gotten where you wanted to go with the
the Santa Clara County I guess let me
just say man this this is probably a
decent segue to I don't know where
you're going next but I suspect it's a
decent segue so all of those critiques
and again I have more which I'm not
going to make your all of those
critiques of this study do not mean that
I think that the overall conclusion is
likely wrong and this is based as you
suggested on some of what we're seeing
elsewhere and on what we understand to
be a high transmission right in in
places like hospitals and nursing homes
and such so I don't find that this study
demonstrates its conclusion to any high
scientific standard but that said a low
CFR even even if the case fatality rate
really is quite low you know a lot of
people are saying you know less than one
percent meaning doesn't mean no CFR
doesn't mean it's not killing people and
deaths are quite high in some places so
that begs the question is the CFR higher
in places like New York City and
Lombardi I don't know or background
rates of infection higher and you know
what what is it you know this this is
where we need the
excellent epidemiology and it's just
moving so fast it's really hard to get
to so um some of the other studies that
have reflected a similarly high base
infection rate and therefore low CF are
rate we're done with very different
methodologies and blood from blood
donors for example was tested and that
doesn't have the same bias of soliciting
people who can drive in from a Facebook
app so it does suggest that there is
reality to this interpretation whether
it varies by location we don't know and
you know the study is some sort of data
it's just compromised by methodological
flaws absolutely
so I guess I mean there's there's a lot
more to say here but the main thing I
would say is case fatality rate gets at
deaths and it may well be that the
biggest lingering effect health effect
put aside the economic effects but the
biggest lingering effect health-wise of
this virus is among the survivors that
we have we are seeing increasingly now
and of course we don't have any
long-term data because this isn't a
long-term situation yet but that people
who survive have respiratory problems of
lung problems have cardiac problems may
have neurological problems that there
are it's it's affecting all of these
systems in the body and of course why
wouldn't it why would we assume that
this respite that this respiratory virus
of this virus that we have named a
respiratory virus would only affect
respiratory systems there's really no
reason to assume that and so focusing
only on the case fatality rate as if
that is a good measure of the effect on
human health and well-being is is not
wise yeah it's it's a hazard I'm
particularly troubled by the fact that
we don't have any good resolution on the
so-called asymptomatic cases whether
they have damage or not and if you have
followed the discussion here and on
Eric's podcast about telomeres the thing
to remember is that
in effect damage pushes you closer to
some threshold from which you cannot
repair right so that threshold at which
you cannot repair some vital tissue is
death right you have a vital tissue it's
gonna fail you can't live without it
so things that damage you push you in
the direction of death
now a lo CFR reflects people who have
not died yet it does not mean they were
not shoved in the direction of death by
15 years it also leaves open questions
which increasingly I hear circulating
about whether a this is a virus that can
recur right without having to be
reinfected whether be you have immunity
once you've had it or it's going to
behave more like colds and flu we're
versions of it will reinfect you
periodically so to the extent that this
is a virus that clearly gives many
people enough of a shove to push them
across the threshold where they can't
get back it's presumably giving many
more people who do get back a shove in
the direction of mortality and then what
is it doing to the people who had a low
symptom or no symptom infection what
will they be like 15 years from an hour
or something like that so anyway all of
these things are important questions and
it points once again to the limitations
of binary thinking dead or not not a
sufficient analysis yes
fully recovered is not fully recovered
and that's true for many many phenomena
right we we medically miscategorized us
or at least the story that we tell does
so I wanted to suggest a couple things
places where we're falling down and then
places where we're succeeding again I'm
stunned by how vibrant how interesting
and how normal the scientific discussion
is this everybody has been reduced to
amateur status even the experts who are
experts at coronaviruses or epidemiology
or whatever are novices with respect to
this particular virus so people are
interacting
in a way that is it's prone to error
I've seen lots of false starts lots of
cul-de-sacs but the fact is the
scientific apparatus is actually
functioning in some ways better than
I've ever seen it function before right
and the fact that you can tune in that
you're not being excluded because you're
not an expert enough to have access to
the literature is wonderful on the other
hand we are even I'll say not only is
most these papers going up in pre print
servers but Elsevier you know one of the
biggest blocks to actually sharing
scientific data out there because it's
one of the big publishers is making its
Cove in nineteen related publications
open at the moment yes this has
embarrassed publishers into behaving as
good citizens which you know is all is
extremely positive the problem is we are
hamstrung by the quality of what there
is to be analyzed and there are a couple
of things that I would suggest here one
of them is that we are unfortunately
being hamstrung by the political
apparatus which has a perverse incentive
and I'm speculating here as to why this
is the case but the Trump administration
for example has been very slow and
reluctant about pushing testing right
and there's a question about why would
anybody not want more testing how could
information possibly be bad and the
answer is that there's a there's a very
reasonable
if immoral argument for eliminating that
data if you are a politician in a
position of authority and it has to do
with what I call monkeying with the
baseline if you are in a position of
authority and you're going to make
decisions and those decisions are gonna
have life-and-death ramifications
they're gonna decide whether or not we
fall into a depression or don't and you
don't want to make a call and have it
come back to haunt you then leaving the
data very vague maximizes the
opportunity to shift the narrative to
push blame on to somebody else so I
remember this first dawn
me after the Fukushima disaster in which
the Shinzo Abe a administration in Japan
began doing all kinds of bizarre stuff
like there was waste that you couldn't
burn because it was too radioactive and
there was a very clear legal standard
about how much radioactivity caused
something not to be viable for
incineration and they would they
justified the adding of non radioactive
material to this radioactive waste in
order to get it below the threshold just
no justification for this at all it does
is add extra pollutants to the
atmosphere but they've gamed their own
standard and then I remember they were
moving waste around the country to burn
it in different places and the only
argument for doing this and I could see
is that later on if you wanted to find
out how bad the Fukushima disaster was
you were gonna have to figure out what
the baseline rate of all of these
cancers was well if you're burning the
radioactive waste in different parts of
the country then the baseline will be
artificially high which will make the
Fukushima disaster look artificially
okay so anyway monkeying with the
baseline is one way to dodge
responsibility and I'm concerned that
what we are facing is a political
apparatus that is playing that game and
blinding us scientifically at a time
when we need high quality vision more
than ever they seem totally willing and
capable of monkeying with the baseline
like this phrase very much Fukushima of
course like Deepwater Horizon as well
was different from what's happening here
in that while there was an event
presumably there was a patient zero
there was an origination of this virus
wherever it came from as we've talked
about in past podcasts our awareness of
it in much of the world was this rolling
awareness right there was not an event a
tsunami or a burst gas line in the case
of Deepwater Horizon and it means that
there was denial followed by possible
embarrassment and then sort of late to
the game I would think comes monkeying
with the baseline hey we can be
opportunistic
and change what's going on it just
doesn't it doesn't look like the
monkeying with the baseline thing is
what was happening earliest at least not
in the US not in the Trump
administration you know maybe depending
what was going on in China that's
possible but it depends a lot on what
was actually happening there well I
think the problem is I don't know how
monkeying with the baseline shows up in
the official discussions but my sense is
it's going to happen everywhere that
responsibility is being apportioned and
you know I think it accounts for some of
what we see in China and a lot of what
we see in the US and when it first dawns
on people that they don't want good data
I don't know and it may be that that
becomes a stance that you even recognize
as a general matter that good data tends
to put you in an awkward spot and so
cloudy data is preferable if you're in a
political position of authority but we
who have to face the the outcomes here
have an interest in forcing our
political apparatus to do right by us
and so I was going to make a suggestion
for in addition to what you have been
saying since the literally moment one on
this which is testing testing testing
that is absolutely the first move here
is to figure out how widespread this
thing is but people who have been paying
attention to these live streams will
remember we talked about the the USS
Theodore Roosevelt the aircraft carrier
that docked in Guam because it had a
infection spreading on board and I
remarked that this was a lost
opportunity because this had been an
isolated population which actually
allowed you to get good data about how
this stuff is spreading and what the
rates of mortality and serious illness
are per infected person yeah that ship
has unsay lizards docked but what I
would I really actually in the middle of
the night last night was that what was
going on that is what was going on is
that military bases might actually
provide the opportunity that we need and
I want to be very careful here I am NOT
suggesting that anybody experiment on
the
Terry there is a very dark history of
that sort of behavior and I'm not
advocating that but what I am suggesting
is that military bases function as
effectively towns they have their towns
with a gate where you know who comes in
and you know who leaves and we've got
built in track and trace right built in
track and trace you have a system of
authority in which people can actually
be you know told do this don't do that
and the question is could these bases be
used a as study locales so could we when
I was thinking is that we would have two
medical teams on a base you would have
the team that was dealing with treating
the patients and unlike is happening in
the world at large you would have an
entirely separate team dealing with
understanding what's taking place right
and that we could discover a how similar
these these outbreaks are be you could
potentially test different things like
different bases could have slightly
different rules about you know whether
you're allowed to go to the park and we
could discover if in fact going to the
park is really a safe thing to do and so
anyway I don't know how it would be done
responsibly but I do believe that there
is a responsible way that would treat
the members of our military with honor
but also allow us to take advantage of
the fact that they already have these
isolated communities established with
all of the tools necessary for us to
understand how you know cause results in
effect and potentially allowing for also
iterated serology testing you know I'm
just adding more and more to what I want
out of the testing apparatus but
widespread antigen testing for current
infection widespread serology testing
for past infection which looks for
antibodies and at most I think people
have been tested twice or if they got
better than they maybe got sick again
maybe a third time but in order to
assess whether or not your first
positive was a positive maybe people you
know it was a false positive a real
positive people get tested twice but I
would love to know what
happens to those titers what happens to
the levels of antibodies over time early
estimates were suggesting that it's a
good seven to ten days after active
infection before you have any noticeable
antibodies in your system and that
climbs for three weeks or so and then
remain steady for no one knows no one
knows as far as I can tell in part
because the tests are are just missing
in action and this is partially due to
errors in the early days at least in the
US and the part of the CDC and such but
it's much more widespread than that so I
would love to see people who do show as
having been infected I would like to
know what happens to their antibody
titers over time which would then begin
to give us a sense possibly as to
whether or not immunity lasts and for
how long
yep so imagine you had a military base
in which everybody was being tracked
from some you know moment zero yeah and
you could simply say well what do we
know about asymptomatic cases and
whether or not they show the same kind
of ground-glass lung damage that shows
up in severe cases well that's an easy
you could test that question I would
imagine in a few days if you had a
population where you could simply
identify here are some people who match
that description let's give them an
x-ray and find out how their lungs look
and then you know track them over time
so in some sense I'm heartened by the
way the scientific apparatus is
functioning I am disheartened by why we
are scratching our heads over what seems
like some of the most basic questions
about the course of this disease even
here you know many weeks down the road
yeah months yeah yeah I agree
well what else do you want to talk about
today we got maybe 15 minutes left um I
think we should talk about the subway
study all right now that I think I do
have open here I think hold on Zack let
me yeah this is it so you can put it on
my put my computer screen on
on okay so this came out of MIT
I don't know this month I don't remember
exactly when oh very recently so the
subways seeded the massive coronavirus
epidemic in New York City
is the title of the working paper
Jeffrey Harris who is an economist and
this paper is a it's a very interesting
paper basically it looks at New York and
it tries to figure out why New York
suffered the the rather impressive rate
of infection that it has faced and as it
says right up front it tested the
hypothesis that that the virus was being
transmitted by the subway and it goes on
to you know the paper is very careful it
says look we don't know whether this is
actually true because the subway is
obviously a non-random network of trains
those trains are built to accommodate at
least the historical understanding of
where people needed to go from and - and
so there are lots of other things that
travel at the same you know in the same
pattern however it does appear to be a
very careful hypothesis test and you may
have heard so the study is it says it's
a correlational study but I believe it's
actually a little too cautious on this
front you know that the correlation
being he's mapped cases I believe it's
just active cases known in various parts
of in zip codes I think it is in New
York City and also then looked actually
maybe I can pull this up he's got he's
got a lot of good maps okay so I can't
want to put this back up just so sorry
to interrupt Brett but just so people
can see what one of the things he's done
is he's got new reported cases in
Manhattan as the red dots here and then
the sky blue bars are turnstile entries
so entries at turnstiles in the subway
system from March 1st through April 4th
I guess where you see that
no strictures were in place I believe
that first week of March and then it
starts decline and it declines quite a
lot and later in the paper he's got this
divided up into the five boroughs and
also looking at differences he does he
does is up a lot see if you can find the
the map he says actually particular
lines are suspect and this one arose why
not yet Zack keep going yeah a lot of
fascinating maps in this paper also I
shall say what are we that's one of them
so this is one line this paper is also
very funny
yeah he uses humor in a way that you
don't tend to see in academic papers
usually presumably it's peer reviewed
out yeah I mean I guess this is part of
what I'm reacting to is that there is
something that has become more honest
about the way people are writing in this
context and so anyway keep scrolling a
little bit I will just say in you want a
different map yeah you want the map that
intersects the two lines
sorry probably giving people vertigo
yeah we are probably giving people
vertigo yeah so okay so Zack to show
this one it's a little hard for me to
parse which which map this is but it
doesn't really matter that the point is
we have a correlational study you have
probably been told that correlation does
not imply causation that is a lie I am
sorry somebody hurt you that way the
truth is that correlation does imply
causation when that correlation maps on
to a pre-existing hypothesis as it does
here it does not say that this locks
down the question that this is causal
but it does say that this is strong
evidence of a causal link because the
hypothesis was being tested by the paper
just with regard to correlation does
imply causation when it maps on to a
pre-existing hypothesis that does not
require that the data didn't exist at
the point that the hypothesis was
formulated with that the person
formulating the hypothesis was not aware
of the data exactly the information was
out there
this guy Harris
said I've got an idea I've got a
hypothesis I think that it was about
Subway ridership that that is related to
that was causing New York City to be
such an epicenter of outbreak and he
then went having made the prediction
into the data and used the de are to
effectively effectively test the
hypotheses although he doesn't make such
a broad claim here yep he's a little
more cautious than I think he needs to
be but he even discovers patterns within
that not only our particular subway
lines implicated but the local trains
are apparently a particular source of
infection if this hypothesis is correct
and the reason is basically that local
trains keep you in contact with other
people longer so a local train is one
that stops at each of the stations along
the way and so if you're going a long
distance on a train and there are no
Express trains you get on the local
train and you're on it longer because
you're stopping at each thing which also
means you're being exposed to more
people so maybe this is obvious to
people but you know it wasn't to our
children we were talking about this last
night you know if you're going from A to
G an express train takes you you get on
an A and it doesn't stop until you get
to G that's quite different from a local
train where it'll not only take you
longer which is why people usually don't
like the local trains if they know
they're going all the way to G but if it
stops at b c d e and f on the way there
are many more possible transmission
points along the way yep and you will
have been exposed to many more people
right that's the transmission points
yeah transmission points okay so they're
points now in any case what he concludes
in this paper is that the reaction of
the Transit Authority doesn't blame them
because they didn't know but what we now
perhaps know but he says the reaction
was the wrong one which was to make all
trains local and to reduce the number of
trains to discourage ridership and the
point is if the mechanism here is right
then the best reaction would have been
to increase the number of trains and
Express trains beat local trains because
you're less likely to be infected in
them he also points out that the fact of
trains interacting with the epidemiology
here is also strongly suggestive of
economic factors and people have been
trying to chase down what are the
economic factors that have certain
populations more afflicted than others
and here would be an obvious one mass
transit yeah if you're condemned to mass
transit and you have a job that you
can't afford to not go to because you
know you're depending on it economically
week to week then you have a recipe for
disaster in some parts of town and not
others apparently the Transit Authority
started cleaning trains twice a day his
point also in the article is you know
what more trains still with the hope
that there is know that there is far
reduced ridership over time but at the
end of each line the trains should be
being cleaned completely yeah now last
point on this I did read one report
which reflected something I have been
wondering about whether somebody needed
to invent this and apparently in Asia
there are already UV robots and
sanitizers that are being used to do
things like clean buses and things so
things like that could be very helpful I
also strongly suspect that HVAC systems
are going to turn out to be a major
villain here and though that's 100
percent we actually have begun already
to see that that information and it's
utterly predicted by the information
from tuberculosis outbreaks from a
century ago and how easy a problem is
that to solve right because basically to
the extent that air is being captured in
one place and filtered through some
system and then pumped back out
elsewhere that air is under your control
and what you basically need to do is
expose whatever passes through it to
extreme enough circumstances that
viruses can't survive be it UV light be
it electromagnetic charge whatever it
would be again then so we have mass
transit which now it's mostly subways
and trains and buses but before
lockdowns was obviously plans we have
know that planes were the major
transmission agent at least between
continents and probably within the
states in between states as well but yet
one more reason go outside be outside
when you can't because your HVAC systems
are going to be pushing stuff around in
ways that you we do not we do not yet
have a control over yeah so all of this
suggests that there will be arbitrary
features of life that differ between
places that will have important
epidemiological impacts and one way to
think about it is that there are
different kinds of reproduction for a
pathogen right the fact that is it more
true if this paper is accurate is it
more true to say that that
SARS Cove 2 is transmitted largely
through aerosolized particles or by
subway right the fact is it actually
it's different scales of transmission
right and a virus that's really
successful like this one is one that is
utilizing many different modes of
transmission over many different scales
and yes it always has to go
person-to-person except in the rare case
that it goes to some other creature but
person-to-person when that person is in
transit over an ocean is obviously its
own its own hazard absolutely to start
thinking at these multiple scales
simultaneously yep all right well that's
about an hour right
I think we've we've done it and we'll be
back okay we'll be back in maybe 15
minutes or so to do an hour of Q&A
addressing your super check questions
all right see you then
[Music]